Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Bertram Metter Papers, 1908-2000 and undated, bulk 1953-1989 RL.00730
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings Series, 1953-1989 and undated, 4 boxes
  - Book manuscript: Breaking the Rules at J. Walter Thompson
    - Research materials (notes, clippings) (Box 5)
      - Various, 1968-1989 and undated (Box 5)
  - Speeches
    - Burt Manning: Human Attitudes and Human Emotions, undated (Box 5)
- Ford Motor Company Account Files Series, 1908-1980s and undated, bulk 1961-1980s, 7 boxes
  Contains advertising concepts (for Ford in general and particular car models), advertising and marketing research, Ford direct mail materials and newsletters, television commercial scripts/storyboards, photographic materials, one folder of historical sheet music (for Ford songs from the 1910s and 1920s), and limited advertisement proofs and headlines. Series is divided into three main categories--car models, marketing research, and photographic materials - and comprises the largest series in the collection. Includes materials on the Ford Escort/Erika, Maverick, Mustang, Olympic, Pinto, Thunderbird, and Torino, arranged alphabetically by model. General marketing research contains Blue Books, Ford Blue Books, marketing/advertising research and strategy, budgeting policies, Ford advertising brochures, and some technical data on cars; arranged chronologically by model year, alphabetically therein. Also includes reprints of historical photographs of the Model T Ford (from the Ford Archives, Henry Ford Museum) and photostats of the Ford Erika (original name for the Ford Escort; by the late 1980s, the Erika/Escort became the best-selling small car in the United States).
  - Car models (Box 5)
    - Erika (early name for Escort)
      - Draft report and competitive advertisements/statistics, 1979 and undated (Box 5)
      - Erika: Where We Are, 1979 Nov. 2 (Box 5)
      - Erika Concepts: Focus Group Research, Phase II, undated (Box 5)
      - Introducing the New World Car: Ford Erika report, 1979 (Box 5)
        Includes one draft along with final report.
      - Meeting agenda, 1979 Dec. 11 (Box 5)
    - Escort
      - Escort OCE Presentation (bound report), 1980 Mar. 7 (Box 5)
    - Expo
      - Featured advertisement in Art Direction, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Falcon
      - About Your New Falcon brochure, undated (Box 5)
        Features Charlie Brown characters.
      - A Scrapbook About Your Falcon, Prepared By Charlie Brown and His Friends, undated (Box 5)
    - Galaxie
      - 1970 model: Galaxie 500 headlines, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Maverick
      - 1969 Price Product Summary, 1969 Aug. 19 (Box 5)
      - Exploratory Study of Introductory Maverick Advertising, 1968 Dec. 5 (Box 5)
      - Maverick X: Advertising timetable for 1975, 1974 (Box 5)
        Includes Metter's handwritten notes.
      - Production information/competitive reports, 1969-1970 (Box 5)
      - Special Maverick research/strategy, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Mustang (Box 6)
      - 1970 headlines, 1969 (Box 6)
    - Olympic
      - 1981 Olympic Concept Exploration (Goldfarb Consultants), 1979 Apr. (Box 6)
    - Pinto
      - 1971 Pinto Pre-Announcement Campaign, circa 1970 (Box 6)
      - 1972 Marketing strategy, circa 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - London marketing, 1971 Sept. (Box 6)
      - Pinto/Maverick: Information sheets, 1964-1970 and undated (Box 6)
        1 item (advertisement proof for Ford Mustang, with Metter's notes about their respective magazine accounts) removed to Oversize Materials, Box OV1.
      - Price/Product Advertising Concept Study, 1971 Mar. 26 (Box 6)
      - Research report on 1972 Pinto Print Campaign, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Schedule, undated (Box 6)
    - Thunderbird
      - 1970 model
        - Headlines, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
        - Production information, 1969 (Box 6)
    - Torino
      - 1970 model: Production information, 1968-1970, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Other
      - Advertising Strategy: Maverick/Tempo/Cortina, circa late 1960s (Box 6)
      - Research memorandum: Thunderbird vs. Sport Luxury Cars, 1968 Feb. 14 (Box 6)
  - Clippings (Box 7)
    - Advertisements
      - Exploring inner space: Small spaceman makes big discoveries about Ford interiors (2-page advertisement spread), circa 1963 (Box 7)
      - Various, circa late 1960s (Box 7)
        Includes advertisements for 1967 Ford and 1968 Thunderbird, and mock Gord advertisement featuring Gordon MacKenzie.
    - Advertising Age: Ford's New World Car Typifies What's New in Auto Marketing (Section 2), 1980 Sept. 29 (Box 7)
    - Chicago Tribune: The Big Change in Ford, The Big Change in Chicago supplement, 1963 Apr. 14 (Box 7)
    - Monthly Detroit: Can Ford Put It Back Together: Portrait of a Company In Trouble, 1980 Apr. (Box 7)
    - New York Times Magazine: Ford: At Ford Everyone Knows Who Is The Boss cover story, 1969 Oct. 19 (Box 7)
    - Wall Street Journal: Sales of Import Cars Boomed in November; 21% Rise Dismays Some Analysts in Detroit, 1969 Dec. 5 (Box 7)
    - WARD'S Auto World: Psychographics: Poking Buyers Personalities, 1981 Apr. (Box 7)
  - Direct mail
    - Car models
      - Falcon
        - 1964 model: Since You Bought Your Falcon and other mailings, 1963 and undated (Box 7)
      - Galaxie
        - About Your New Galaxie, circa early 1960s (Box 7)
      - Thunderbird
        - 1963 model catalog, circa 1962 (Box 7)
        - Limited Edition Landau, 1963 Feb. (Box 7)
    - Various mailings
      - 1961 model brochure: Ripley's Believe It or Not: Some Amazing Facts About Your '61 Ford, undated (Box 7)
      - 1963 model: Why Ford officials don't always drive Fords, circa 1962 (Box 7)
      - 1964 passenger car campaign: What Made These Plymouth Owners Change Their Minds? 1964 Mar. (Box 7)
      - Free Silver Dollar campaign, 1961 and undated (Box 7)
      - Meet the Lively Ones and Is One Stop Enough When You're Buying A Car? mailings, circa 1961-1962 (Box 7)
      - New York District F.D.A.F. Owner Loyalty Program: A Direct Mail Campaign to New Ford Buyers, undated (Box 7)
      - Special Report to Women Car Owners on the New '64s, 1963 (Box 7)
      - Station wagon promotion: Living It Up: A Story of Fun, Fads..., undated (Box 7)
      - To showroom visitors: Why We Called the Police on the Carpet... and For Second Lookers Only, circa 1962-1963, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Ford Owner Newsletter, 1961-1964 and undated, 15 folders (Box 7)
    Includes Buyer's Digest of New Car Facts For 1964, originally mailed with January 1964 newsletter and included in that folder.
  - Ford Times, 1972 Jan.-Feb. (Box 7)
  - Headlines, 1969-1970 (Box 7)
  - Marketing research
    - 1968 model year
      - Competitive Evaluation (Ford, Mustang, Falcon, Thunderbird, Wagons), 1967 Oct. 24 (Box 7)
      - Creative Strategy for 1968 Ford Division Advertising, 1967 Apr. 27 (Box 7)
      - Forward Planning (New Concept Falcon and Escort), circa 1967-1968 (Box 7)
      - Introduction Day Study (Ford Division) and Competitive Make Cars, 1967 Sept. (Box 7)
        Survey of the 1968 model year's first day introduction at dealers.
      - 1968 Ford Car Product Review (report by Jim Whipple), 1967 June 22 (Box 7)
      - Sales and Advertising Presentation, 1966 Dec. 13 (Box 7)
    - 1969 model year
      - Forward Planning, circa 1968 (Box 7)
    - 1970 model year (Box 8)
      - Forward Planning, 1969 and undated, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Research and development/advertising timetables, 1968-1969 (Box 8)
    - 1971 model year
      - Blue Books
        - 1971 Cars, 1970 Jan. 21 (Box 8)
        - 1971 Mustang Competition (including Camaro and Barracuda), 1971 (Box 8)
        - Leadership '71: The Challenge of Change, 1971 (Box 8)
        - A Spokesman for Ford Division, 1970 Jan. 26 (Box 8)
        - Suggested Marketing and Advertising Strategy: January Through June 1971, 1971 (Box 8)
          Report drafted to address anticipated Ford and/or General Motors strike.
        - Summary: 1971 Concept Studies, 1971 Feb. 15 (Box 8)
      - Ford Blue Books
        - 1971 Ford Cars (marketing ideas), 1970 Jan. 26, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - 1971 Ford Division Advertising, 1970 Jan. 30 (Box 8)
        - 1971 Ford Division Car Line, Presentation to J. Walter Thompson Co., 1969 Aug. 28 (Box 8)
        - 1971 Ford Division Theme, 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Advertising Strategy for 1971, 1969-1970 (Box 8)
        - Ford Division: 1971 Preliminary Car Advertising Strategy, 1969 Oct. 9 (Box 8)
        - January–August Advertising Program, 1969-1970 (Box 8)
        - Marketing Ideas, 1969-1970 (Box 9)
        - Recommended Advertising and Merchandising Strategy/Meeting, 1969-1970 (Box 9)
        - Suggested Marketing & Advertising Strategy (January-June 1971), circa 1970 (Box 9)
      - Forward Planning, 1969-1970, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - 1971-1972 model year
      - Market research reports, 1970-1971 (Box 9)
        Includes reports: Automobile Market Segment Percentages, 1957-1970, 1971 Model Early Buyer Study, 4-Door Pinto and Vega, Consumer Reactions to Three Alternative Maverick (Print & TV) Campaigns.
    - 1972 model year
      - 1972 Ford Division cars (meetings with Naughton, Zimmerman, Fisher), 1971 June, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Models/Scripts, 1971 (Box 9)
    - 1980 model year
      - Forward Product Plans: report and clippings, 1979-1980 and undated (Box 9)
    - 1983 model year
      - Positioning the 1983 Fords, circa early 1980s (Box 9)
    - General reports
      - America's Baby Boom and the Automotive Market: 1983 Report by J.D. Power & Associates, 1983-1984 (Box 9)
      - Analysis of Consumer Reactions to the Use of Cartoon Characters in the Advertising Strategy for Ford Maverick, 1971 Apr. (Box 9)
      - Analysis of Starch Readership Data Automobile Advertising, 1968 Jan. (Box 9)
      - Brazil Ford, 1972 and 1977 (Box 10)
      - Brief Fact Sheets: TV Commercial Testing Services, 1970 May (Box 10)
      - Budgeting Policies for Ford, 1965 (Box 10)
      - Consumer Reactions to Five 1972 Animatic Television Commercials (Prepared by Rogers National Research), 1971 June 25 (Box 10)
      - Consumer Response to Two Print Approaches for Ford Advertising, 1971 May (Box 10)
      - Continuing Attitude Study of Car Owners (conducted February 1971), 1971 May 11 (Box 10)
      - Dealer calls, 1967 Sept. (Box 10)
      - Ford Advertising Concept Study: Consumer Attitudes Toward Size in a Car, 1968 Feb. 19 (Box 10)
      - Ford vs Chevrolet Division Owner Loyalty By Car Line, 1970 July 23 (Box 10)
      - General Motors Major Features Summary--1968 models, 1967 Sept. 1 (Box 10)
      - Group Sessions Conducted on Preliminary 1968 Advertising Approaches, 1967 Mar. 17 (Box 10)
      - Implications of the Young, Upwardly Mobile Professional Market for Ford Division Marketing Strategy, 1983 Oct. 4 (Box 10)
      - Information concerning Quiet Theme, 1971 Feb. 16 (Box 10)
      - Market Pulse study, 1983-1984 (Box 10)
      - NAAO Assignment: 'Focusing the Spotlight on Ford,' 1984 Apr. 4 (Box 10)
      - NFL (National Football League) Sponsorship
        - 1968 Promotion, undated (Box 10)
        - Radio Promotion concepts, undated (Box 10)
      - Network and Engineering Comments, 1970 (Box 10)
      - The New Consumer Opinion on Ford’s Quality and the Relevance of Quality in the Purchase Decision, 1967 May 10 (Box 10)
      - Refocusing the Spotlight on Ford: A Market Research Review of Car Owner Attitudes (U.S. and Canada), 1984 Feb. (Box 10)
        Full report included in the appendix to NAAO Assignment: 'Focusing the Spotlight on Ford' (folder in Box 10).
      - Research Results of the 1963 Spending Level Experiment, 1967 June 26 (Box 10)
      - Sound Level Noise Tests (conducted by Edward Schott), 1967 Sept.-Oct. (Box 10)
      - Starch Reports, 1969-1970 and undated (Box 10)
      - Study of Two Introductory 1968 Ford Print Ads (prepared by Brand, Gruber and Company), 1967 Apr. (Box 10)
      - Ten Day Reports, 1968 and 1970 (Box 10)
      - Time As A Commodity (Time Saver), 1971 Apr. 20 (Box 10)
      - Uniform Procedure for pre-testing (research summary for four Ford commercials), circa late 1960s (Box 10)
      - White Sale (Special value vehicles), 1969-1970 (Box 10)
    - Report: Washington calls for the 'Can Do' men, undated (Box 11)
    - Research memoranda, 1970-1971 (Box 11)
    - Strategy/Image (Bonus Plan, NAAO Assignment, Warranty), 1983-1984 and undated (Box 11)
      Includes Warranty Information booklets.
  - Photographic materials
    - Photographs
      - Historical photographs, 1911, 1915 and undated (Box 11)
        Includes photographs reprinted from the Ford Archives, Henry Ford Museum in Dearborn, Michigan. Features the Model T in particular, many photographs included in the Ford Times.
    - Photostats
      - Erika: Commercial storyboards for 1981 model, 1979 and undated (Box 11)
  - Sheet music, 1908-1923 and undated (Box 11)
    Photocopies of sheet music for popular songs promoting early Ford cars: The Ford: March Two-Step, On the Old Back Seat Of The Henry Ford, The Little Ford Rambled Right Along, Hurrah For Henry That Builds the Famous Ford, and Henry Ford. Music from the Ford Archives, Henry Ford Museum in Dearborn, Michigan.
- Other Clients Series, 1969-2000 and undated, bulk 1969-1972, 2 boxes
  Contains materials in a variety of formats--headlines, press clippings, television commerical scripts and storyboards, marketing research and notes--relating to JWT clients other than Ford, most notably Pepsi-Cola (Mexico) and Liggett & Myers. Other clients represented by fewer materials are Bristol Myers, Firestone, Hertz, Lever, and Listerine. Also includes general marketing research and new business materials Metter generated at JWT and as a consultant. Of particular interest is a memorandum outlining procedure for the use of musical compositions in radio and television productions. Arranged into three categories--general marketing research, JWT clients, and new business--and alphabetically therein.
  - General marketing research (Box 11)
    - Financial research: Regional trends graph, undated (Box 11)
    - Major Multinational Client Profitability report, circa 1987 (Box 11)
    - Preliminary Report on New York Research Department, 1970 July 16 (Box 11)
    - Procedure to be Followed for Use of Musical Compositions in Television and Radio Commercials, 1971 Jan. 14 (Box 11)
  - JWT clients
    - Firestone, 1969-1971 and undated, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Lever: Laundry Problems/Solutions and Fabric Softeners, 1972 and undated (Box 11)
    - Liggett & Myers: Eve Cigarettes
      - Advertisements: Headlines and concepts/proofs, undated (Box 11)
      - Bound reports
        - A Copt Test of Two Print Ads for Eve Cigarettes, 1970 Oct. (Box 11)
        - Creative Development Program for Eve Cigarettes, 1970 Sept. (Box 11)
        - A Diagnostic Study of Two Print Ads for Eve Cigarettes, 1971 Aug. (Box 11)
        - Filter Brand Smoker Images: Part II --Competing Brands (Liggett & Myers Market Research Department), circa 1971 (Box 11)
      - Lark cigarettes: Test Marketing Plan/Focus Groups, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Memoranda and reports--Various, 1970-1971 and undated, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Listerine (cold tablets): television advertising concepts and consumer reports, 1969-1970 and undated (Box 12)
    - Pepsi-Cola (Mexico)
      Materials primarily in English.
      - Advertising campaigns
        - Connoisseurs, 1971 (Box 12)
        - Insisters/No Excuses (Don't give me any Jazz, give me a Pepsi), 1971 (Box 12)
        - Our Taste, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 12)
        - Sí (Say Yes), 1971-1972 (Box 12)
        - You Deserve, 1971 (Box 12)
        - Various (General campaign objectives/miscellaneous concepts), 1971 (Box 12)
      - General research and reports
        - 1972 Advertising Campaign (South America Recommendation), 1971 Oct. (Box 12)
        - Exploration of Motivations of Consumers in Six Countries Toward Pepsi-Cola: Addendum on Mexico, 1969 July (Box 12)
        - Pepsi-Cola in Mexico report (overview of 4 campaigns), 1971 (Box 12)
        - Pepsi Copy Strategy report, 1971 (Box 12)
  - New business
    - JWT
      - Bristol-Myers, 1970-1971 (Box 12)
      - Emery: Emery: Some Thoughts memorandum, 1984 (Box 12)
      - Hertz, 1971-1973 and undated (Box 12)
      - Watches, 1973 (Box 12)
    - Metter
      - Affinity (Internet company): correspondence/concepts, 2000 and undated (Box 12)
        Includes Newsweek direct mail materials as part of Metter's client portfolio.
- Oversize Materials, 1963-1989 and undated, 1 box
  Primarily includes oversize clippings from the Professional Files Series and Writings Series; also contains large-format materials from the Ford Motor Company Account Files Series and Other Clients Series. Arranged within original series, therein alphabetically.
  - Professional Files Series (Box OV1)
    - Industry publications
      - Advertising Age
        - Clippings--Various, 1966-1985 and undated (Box OV1)
        - Issues: 1980 Sept. 1; 1988 Apr. 4; 1989 Nov. 27, 3 folders (Box OV1)
        - Supplements/Special issues
          - Twentieth Century Advertising and the Economy of Abundance: A Review of 50 Years of American Advertising, its Economic and Social Importance, and its Contribution to the American Standard of Living, 1980 Apr. 30 (Box OV1)
          - U.S. Advertising Agency Profiles: 1988 Edition, 1988 Mar. 30 (Box OV1)
      - Automotive News, 1980 and 1983 (Box OV1)
      - Back Stage: The complete service weekly for the communications and entertainment industry, 1984 Oct. 19 (Box OV1)
      - The New York Times, 1985 and 1988 (Box OV1)
      - Shooting Commercials: Music page (Vol. 6, No. 5), 1983 May (Box OV1)
    - JWT
      - Advertisement clippings: New York Times and Wall Street Journal, 1983, 1985 and undated (Box OV1)
        Advertisements on best-liked TV campaigns, taglines include: How come a big, conservative ad agency is creating America's most outstanding advertising? and Main Street ranks Madison Avenue.
      - Newsletters: The New York Thompson (Vol. III, No. 3), 1980 May 1 (Box OV1)
  - Writings Series (Box OV1)
    - Chapter drafts: Research/clippings
      - Chapters 4-5 and 7, 1967-1987 and undated (Box OV1)
      - Chapters 10-17, 1986-1988 and undated (Box OV1)
      - Chapters 18-20, 1987-1989 and undated (Box OV1)
    - Chapter outline/cover pages, 1987 and undated (Box OV1)
    - Research clippings--Miscellaneous
      - Advertising Age, 1987-1989 (Box OV1)
      - Various (The New York Times, Wall Street Journal), 1987-1988 and undated (Box OV1)
  - Ford Motor Company Account Files Series (Box OV1)
    - Car models
      - Erika (Mitsubishi competitive advertisement), 1979 (Box OV1)
      - Pinto/Maverick information sheets: Advertisement proof for Ford Mustang (includes Metter's notes about Pinto vs. Mustang magazine accounts), 1964 (Box OV1)
    - Clippings
      - Advertisements
        - Exploring inner space: Small spaceman makes big discoveries about Ford interiors (2-page advertisement spread), circa 1963 (Box OV1)
        - Various, circa late 1960s (Box OV1)
      - Advertising Age: Ford's New World Car Typifies What's New in Auto Marketing (Section 2), 1980 Sept. 29 (Box OV1)
      - Chicago Tribune: The Big Change in Ford, The Big Change in Chicago supplement, 1963 Apr. 14 (Box OV1)
      - New York Times Magazine: At Ford Everyone Knows Who Is The Boss cover story, 1969 Oct. 19 (Box OV1)
    - Marketing research
      - 1970 model: Forward Planning--Competitive slogan chart, undated (Box OV1)
  - Other Clients Series (Box OV1)
    - Pepsi-Cola (Mexico): Advertising Campaigns-- Sí (Say Yes) storyboards, circa 1971 (Box OV1)